[MUSIC PLAYING] https://youtu.be/bQRwUhCpR6Y
[NHẠC] https://youtu.be/bQRwUhCpR6Y
ERIKA NAGINSKI: My name is Erika Naginski.
ERIKA NAGINSKI: Tên tôi là  Erika Naginski.
I am Professor of Architectural History at the Graduate School of Design
Tôi là giáo sư môn Lịch sử kiến trúc của trường Sau đại học về Thiết kế,
and the Director of the PhD program in Architecture, Landscape Architecture,
và là Giám đốc chương trình đào tạo tiến sĩ về Kiến trúc, Kiến trúc cảnh quan
and Urbanism.
và Chủ nghĩa đô thị.
Today, we're going to be talking about the relationship of a book that
Hôm nay, chúng ta sẽ nói về mối quan hệ giữa một cuốn sách
was published in 1949 by Rudolf Wittkower entitled "Architectural
của Rudolf Wittkower, dược xuất bản năm 1949
Principles in the Age of Humanism" and its characterization of the Renaissance
với tựa đề "Những nguyên tắc kiến trúc trong thời đại nhân văn" và
architect.
kiến trúc sư thời Phục Hưng.
As we'll see, this is a book that had an extraordinary impact
Như chúng ta sẽ thấy, đây là một cuốn sách có tác động đặc biệt
on two distinct groups.
đến hai nhóm người riêng biệt.
The first was the Renaissance architectural historian.
Nhóm thứ nhất là các sử gia về kiến trúc thời kỳ Phục Hưng.
This book offered a new approach to the way
Cuốn sách này đem đến một cách tiếp cận mới
we understand the architecture of the 15th and the 16th century in Italy.
đối với cách mà chúng ta hiểu về kiến trúc thế kỷ 15 và 16 ở Ý.
The other group was the modernist architect.
Nhóm còn lại là các kiến trúc sư theo chủ nghĩa tân thời.
It is strange to think that a book on the Renaissance
Thật lạ khi nghĩ rằng một cuốn sách về thời Phục Hưng
might have an impact on modernist thinking,
có thể tác động đến tư duy hiện đại.
but this book revolutionized our understanding of geometry,
Tuy nhiên, cuốn sách này đã cách mạng hóa sự hiểu biết của chúng ta về hình học,
modular pattern, and the ways in which diagrams can be used
và cách sử dụng sơ đồ
to explain the work of the architect.
dể giải thích về công trình của kiến trúc sư.
Two things to say about this book.
Có hai điều để nói về cuốn sách này.
The first is that it was highly invested in an abstract and intellectual
Thứ nhất, cuốn sách được đầu tư kỹ lưỡng theo một cách tiếp cận trừu tượng và trí tuệ
approach to the Renaissance.
đối với thời Phục Hưng.
It underscored the rise of theory in the 15th and 16th century,
Nó nhấn mạnh lý thuyết trong thế kỉ 15 và 16,
and the ways in which the works of a given architect
và cách thức mà các tác phẩm của một kiến trúc sư cụ thể
might offer a coherent kind of investigation
có thể
into a set of problems surrounding perspective, proportion, geometry,
về một chuỗi các vấn đề xung quanh quan điểm, sự cân xứng, hình học
and the advent of ideal form and architecture.
và sự xuất hiện của hình thức và kiến trúc lý tưởng.
This highly abstract approach had repercussions.
Cách tiếp cận trìu tượng này có tác động trở lại.
What it means, ironically, is that Wittkower was absolutely disinvested
What it means, ironically, is that Wittkower was absolutely disinvested
from the complexities of history.
from the complexities of history.
He was not interested in the cultural context
Ông không quan tâm đến bối cảnh văn hóa
out of which architecture arose.
nảy sinh ra kiến trúc.
He does not delve into patronage, religious history, the monastic orders,
Ông không đào sâu vào lịch sử tôn giáo, các luật dòng ở tu viện,
particular events that might have marked the Renaissance.
hay những sự kiện cụ thể đánh dấu thời kì Phục Hưng.
Instead, he steps back to analyze architectural form
Thay vào đó, ông suy ngẫm để phân tích hình thức kiến trúc
as an autonomous project.
như một tự trị.
At the heart of this approach is the notion of the paradigm.
Trọng tâm của phương pháp này là khái niệm về mô hình
The word paradigm comes from the Greek.
Từ "mô hình" bắt nguồn từ tiếng Hy Lạp,
It means both pattern and to show side-by-side.
It means both pattern and to show side-by-side.
In the latter definition, really get a sense
Trong cách định nghĩa thứ hai,
of a comparative approach, that to put two things
of a comparative approach, that to put two things
together means essentially the creation of a synthesis.
về cơ bản có nghĩa là tạo ra sự tổng hợp.
So the word ultimately serves to underscore the creation
Như vậy, từ này dùng để nhấn mạnh việc tạo ra
of an outstanding example of something.
một nổi bật của thứ gì đó,
Of a model, a standard, an epitome, an ideal, a paragon.
chẳng hạn như một mô hình, một tiêu chuẩn,
The assumption on Wittkower's part is that Renaissance architects
các kiến trúc sư thời Phục Hưng
were after such paradigms, that they sought and developed them,
tìm kiếm và phát triển
and ultimately, through that process, were after the core principles
và cuối cùng, qua quá trình này,
of architectural form.
of architectural form.
By the same token, what's also true is that Wittkower's very own approach
là cách tiếp cận riên của Wittkower
became paradigmatic.
dã trở nên
In other words, it offered a standard means
Nói cách khác, nó này đem đến một cách thức tiêu chuẩn
of approaching the historical past, of interpreting the past, and even
dể tiếp cận quá khứ lịch sử, giải thích lịch sử
of generating form itself.
và thậm chí là tạo
How do we understand this book?
Chúng ta hiểu cuốn sách này như thế nào?
Is it an interpretation of Renaissance architecture?
Đó có phải là một sự giải thích về kiến trúc thời Phục Hưng?
Is it a template for modernist architectural thinking?
Đó có phải là khuôn mẫu cho lối tư duy kiến trúc hiện đại?
What we can say is that Wittkower's is a broad attempt
Những gì ta có thể nói đó là
to characterize the theory of architecture
để mô tả lý thuyết của kiến trúc.
as it emerged in the 15th and 16th century in a distinct set of places.
khí nó xuất hiện vào thế kỉ 15 và 16
In Florence, in Rome, and in Venice.
Ở Florence, Rome và Venice.
Furthermore, the book is broken up into four chapters
Hơn nữa, cuốn sách được chia làm bốn chương
that deal with issues that Wittkower took to be absolutely fundamental.
nói về những vấn đề mà Wittkower cho là hoàn toàn cơ bản.
First, there is the question of symbolism.
Thứ nhất là câu hỏi về chủ nghĩa tượng trưng.
In other words, how buildings mean.
Nói cách khác, các tòa nhà có ý nghĩa như thế nào.
The second chapter looks at the problem of the appropriation of form.
Chương hai xem xét vấn đề
In other words, how did architects look back
Nói cách khác, các kiến trúc sư dã nhìn lại quá khứ sâu xa,
to the deep past, and in particular, to the pagan classical past,
mà cụ thể là quá khứ cổ điển ngoại giáo,
seize that tradition, reinterpret in syntax
nắm bắt truyền thống đó, diễn giải lại trong cú pháp
and reinvent classicism as a system.
và tái tạo chủ nghĩa cổ điển như một hệ thống.
Third, the question of typology and the development of building types.
Thứ ba, câu hỏi về các loại hình học và sự phát triển của các loại kiến trúc.
Are we talking about churches?
Chúng ta dang nói về nhà thở?
Are we talking about villas?
Chúng ta đang nói về các căn biệt thự?
Are we talking about institutional buildings?
Chúng ta đang nói về các tòa nhà thể chế?
And lastly, the question of proportion.
Và cuối cùng, câu hỏi về sự cân xứng.
The geometric ideal.
hình học.
The question of measure.
Câu hỏi về do lường.
And while any number of architects, buildings, texts
Trong khi kiến trúc sư,
are invoked in his book, it's also clear that there are essentially
rõ ràng rằng có hai chính
two key players in his narrative.
two key players in his narrative.
The first we'll talk about today is Alberti, a theorist and an architect.
Người đầu tiên mà chúng ta sẽ đề cập đến hôm nay là Albeti, một nhà lý thuyết và một kiến trúc sư.
A real Renaissance man.
một
He was also a painter.
Ông cũng là một họa sỹ.
And second, a Venetian architect from the 16th century named Andrea Palladio.
Thứ hai là một kiến trúc sư thế kỷ 16 có tên là Andrea Palladio.
These two figures essentially represent the whole
Về cơ bản, hai nhân vật này đại diện
of the Italian Renaissance for Wittkower,
cho toàn bộ thời kỳ phục hưng ở Ý,
and when we think about that, we understand that Wittkower's approach
và khi nghĩ về điều này, chúng ta hiểu rằng cách tiếp cận của Wittkower
was essentially reductive.
was essentially reductive.
What might we expect the historian to garner
What might we expect the historian to garner
from a picture of the Renaissance architect or the buildings
from a picture of the Renaissance architect or the buildings
that he erected?
that he erected?
We might assume that the historian would be after a history of patronage,
Gỉa định rằng sử gia sẽ
for example.
for example.
A history of the politics that gave rise to a particular commission.
A history of the politics that gave rise to a particular commission.
Who would consider the great events that marked the 15th and 16th century.
Ai sẽ đánh dấu thế kỷ 15 và 16.
Changes in military technology.
Những thay đổi trong công nghệ quân sự.
Also, the question of politics or religion during this period.
câu hỏi về chính trị hay tốn giáo trong giai đoạn này.
The influence of the papacy.
Ảnh hưởng của chế độ giáo hoàng.
The rise of ducal states and their sense of an autonomy from the papacy.
The rise of ducal states and their sense of an autonomy from the papacy.
To read Wittkower is to see a process of mental abstraction at work.
quá trình
In other words, what Wittkower was after wasn't
Nói cách khác, những gì mà
the discrete cultural meaning of a particular building
the discrete cultural meaning of a particular building
in a particular context.
in a particular context.
He's not after giving us some real and robust sense of the 16th century world
Ông không
view.
view.
Instead, he wants to bring together the classical kit of parts
Thay vào đó, ông muốn
that make a building formalize itself, that
that make a building formalize itself, that
allow it to transform into the buildings we still have today.
allow it to transform into the buildings we still have today.
In other words, Wittkower is looking for a kind of deep structure,
Nói cách khác, Wittkower đang tìm kiếm một loại cấu trúc
we might call it, that organizes architectural form.
we might call it, that organizes architectural form.
He's going after the identification of their component parts.
He's going after the identification of their component parts.
What is a portico?
Cổng xây là gì?
What is a column?
What is a column?
This is why ultimately, he relies on diagrams to explain architecture.
Đó là lý do tại sao cuối cùng ông lại dự vào sơ đồ để giải thích kiến trúc.
He looks through the complex appearance of a building like this
Ông nhìn qua vẻ bề ngoài phức tạp của một tòa nhà như thế này
in all its three-dimensionality and distills it
và
into its most basic elements through plan, sometimes elevation.
thành những yếu tố cơ bản nhất
In other words, he develops a syntax, a language, a form.
Nói cách khác, ông phát triển một ngôn ngữ, một hình thức.
He's interested in Renaissance architecture as an explicitly--
Ông quan tâm đến kiến trúc thời Phục Hưng
and these are his words--
and these are his words--
as an explicitly "mathematical science which worked with spatial units."
as an explicitly "mathematical science which worked with spatial units."
Wittkower's whole analysis along these lines
Wittkower's whole analysis along these lines
can be understood as a philosophical exercise, not an historical analysis.
có thể được hiểu là một bài tập về triết học, chứ không phải phân tích lịch sử.
In which thinking and reason emerge as the defining
Trong đó, tư duy và lý trí nổi lên
characteristics of the architect.
như những đặc điểm xác định của người kiến trúc sư.
And this is what's demonstrated through the diagrams.
Và đây là những gì dược chứng minh thông qua sơ đồ.
Ultimately, what emerges from this is the autonomy of architecture itself.
Rốt cuộc thì, những gì nổi lên từ đây là quyền tự trị của kiến trúc.
And we see this when we look at what his diagram of the Villa Cornaro does.
Chúng ta nhận thấy khi nhìn vào những gì mà sơ đồ
You can see that he's interested only in the plan.
Các bạn có thể thấy rằng ông chỉ quan tâm đến kế hoạch.
He cuts away the rear monumental staircase.
những cầu thang
He minimizes and essentially elides the entrance porch, takes away the column,
Ông và
and therefore anything that might signify a supportive function.
and therefore anything that might signify a supportive function.
He takes away the side wings.
He takes away the side wings.
He takes away the poche, the scale, everything, in other words,
He takes away the poche, the scale, everything, in other words,
that Palladio indicates in his plan and elevation.
that Palladio indicates in his plan and elevation.
We want to think about how these diagrams give us
We want to think about how these diagrams give us
a certain highly particular view of the Renaissance, which privileges geometry,
a certain highly particular view of the Renaissance, which privileges geometry,
all the way from its basic spatial units to the general order given
all the way from its basic spatial units to the general order given
to the universe by God.
to the universe by God.